Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna.
We're going to start
with some Sanskrit words
that are good to know
for the tough task ahead
of further exploring that special moment
when everything you need
for something to happen
has come together,
and what you want to happen
is about to pop out.
That point in time...
We here in the studio,
we were discussing is there
a good English word for that.
There were some words,
there's an idiom, you say
"Everything came together,"
or something like that.
But we don't have a single word for it.
In Sanskrit, there is
a single word for it.
And that's 'sāmagryā'. Say sāmagryā.
- [Students] Sāmagryā.
- Sāmagryā, yeah.
You can see it here.
When the causes and
conditions do come together,
that's called sāmagryā.
I started to try to work
on breaking this word down.
Right, Cristina? This
is what we normally do.
And sāma in Tibetan is
DUMS, DUMS PO,
which means for everything
to come together.
So I thought "Oh, here I'm on a roll."
Sāma is together, so
gryā must be come, or,
maybe it is related to
@gr - to grab, or to come.
And then I checked Monier-Williams,
which is probably the
greatest Sanskrit dictionary
of all time.
And he said "No, no, no,
it comes from sam-agra."
Sam-agra.
Yeah, Christina, as you just
said, 'agra' means the tip.
Like the steps of SBYOR LAM -
DROD, RTZE MO, BZOD PA, CHOS CHOG.
RTZE MO, the second one, or the city Agra,
where the Taj Mahal is located.
Agra means the tip or the top point.
In Monier-Williams it's explained as
sam-agra.
So it comes from sam-agra,
'sam' meaning totally,
and also 'come together',
and then agra means tip,
which means the pinnacle.
So think of it as that way:
the pinnacle of readiness
or the pinnacle of conjunction.
Because everything came
together perfectly, agra.
Okay?
So, he claims it comes from that.
That would normally be a push
on the way it looks to me,
but I think it's fine.
It makes a good story,
as they say.
And by the way, discussing
these points in Sanskrit
can be endless over the centuries.
People have tried over the centuries.
I think if you find one
that sounds reasonable
and also tells a story,
or tells a useful point,
I'll take it.
If it helps my students
to remember the pieces,
I'll take it.
The second word I'd
like you guys to learn,
is 'phala'.
Phala.
And in Tibetan it's 'BRAS BU
The verbal root /phal means to fruit,
or to ripen as a fruit.
It also means to expand
or burst like a balloon.
And the words full, the
words pure, the word ball,
the word pore, as in Singapore, Rajapore.
Singapore means full of lions.
And then pura became the word for city,
because it means full of people.
So, again, P can change
to F, R can change to L,
and you get 'full'.
From all these: phala.
The idea of a fruit expanding
until it's ready to pop open,
and then you bite into it.
So that's phala.
In Sanskrit, that's result.
So, these are going to be
easy to remember, right?
Sāmagryā,
the tip of everything coming together.
And then phala meaning fruit.
Whoever's outside can come
in, if they're wondering.
I think it's Jasso.
Now we've reached another
point in the outline.
We had already examined,
is the opening of the
cafe, somehow present
in the final coming together
of everything you need to open the cafe?
We had arguments for
and arguments against.
And now Choney Lama says,
the next verse of Nagarjuna,
you can consider DE LA
YOD MED NYID DGAG PA
Actually, we just denied
the two possibilities
that the opening of the cafe was present
in the coming together
of everything you need
to open the cafe.
And we also denied the possibility
that it wasn't present somehow.
Or else anything could come out
of all the causes coming together.
Now, he says "Let's deny
the possibility of both."
Okay? That it is there
and it isn't there.
Okay?
So, he changes the wording here.
He doesn't say, "Does a result
which is already present
in the conditions arise?"
Now he just says, "Is
it even a possibility?"
So a little bit different,
different shade.
We're not discussing "Can
that result pop out?"
We're discussing does
it even make sense to say
it does or doesn't exist
at the time of the assembling
of the conditions?
Final perfect assembly of the conditions.
Sāmagryā.
All right, here we go.
,GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS KYI,
,TSOGS LA 'BRAS BU YOD NA NI,
,TSOGS LA GZUNG DU YOD RIGS NA,
,TSOGS PA NYID LA GZUNG DU MED,
,GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS KYI,
,TSOGS LA ‘BRAS BU MED NA NI,
,RGYU RNAMS DANG NI RKYEN DAG KYANG,
,RGYU RKYEN MA YIN MTSUNGS PAR ‘GYUR,
And as you see, I'm always...
well, you can't see it here.
It's an interesting point
that the version of Nagarjuna
being used by Choney Lama
is slightly different than
the version of Nagarjuna
I found in John Brady's
database in the Tengyur.
So what we have here is probably
one of the early translations
of an ancient Indian book
that didn't make it as a choice.
And Tsongkapa likes to say,
"I like to read the ones that
didn't make it into the Tengyur
because sometimes they're better."
Or sometimes some of
the verses are better.
So you can imagine.
50 years from now, people trying to choose
which translation of this book
is going to be the standard.
Whichever they choose, is
going to have some weaknesses
that were not present in
some of the alternatives.
And what we have here,
if you're really a textual nerd,
you have a version that
was popular somehow
even before the final decision was made.
There are some interesting differences
and they tell stories.
They're profitable to study,
if you have lots of free time.
[students giggle]
But if people are texting you all morning
it's not probable.
[students giggle]
GZHAN YANG GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN
RNAMS KYI TSOGS PA LA 'BRAS BU BRTEN PA'I
SGO NAS YOD NA NI
Now he says...
Let's not discuss whether or not
the opening of the cafe is present
in the convening of everything
you need to open the cafe,
like a jewel in a ring.
Let's not look at it that way.
Let's look at it this way.
Is it present in an implied way,
in that it leans upon the convening
of the causes and conditions?
It rests upon or it depends upon
the convening of...
So let's not say it's nested
in the causes and conditions.
Let's looks at whether it can rely on
the causes and conditions.
If it can lean on the
causes and conditions.
Can it be present in the sense
of leaning on the causes and conditions?
So it's a little bit different, right?
Not -- is it present nested in
the causes and conditions?
Is it present leaning on
So that's what we're going to look at now.
GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS KYI
TSOGS LA 'BRAS BU MED NA NI
I'm sorry.
GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS KYI TSOGS PA LA
‘BRAS BU BRTEN PA’I SGO NAS
YOD NA NI MI ‘THAD DE,
If you say the result is present
in the convening of all the
necessary causes and conditions,
in the sense of leaning on them,
DE YIN NA TSOGS PA LA 'BRAS BU
DNGOS SU GZUNG DU YOD RIGS NA
in that case, it should
be, somehow detectable
in the causes and conditions.
If it were leaning on the
causes and conditions,
if it were present in the sense
of the glass resting upon the table,
then it should somehow be perceivable
in the causes and conditions.
If it were the necessary appendage
of the causes and conditions,
then when you saw the
causes and conditions,
you should somehow be
able to see the result
that's going to come out of
the causes and conditions.
It should be present like
a cup resting on the table.
He says, "But that's not right."
DE YIN NA TSOGS PA LA 'BRAS BU DNGOS SU
GZUNG DU YOD RIGS NA
If it were present in the act of leaning
on the causes and conditions or resting
on the causes and conditions,
then it should be detectable
by some correct perception, right?
We said that was the
definition of existence.
But it's not.
There's no way you can perceive
the actual operating cafe in the presence
of the building, and the
capital, and the uncooked food.
You see what I mean? You cannot see it.
It's not observable in
the causes and conditions
before it pops up.
So cancel that idea.
Now, how is he going to go next?
You tell me.
I'll say what he said so far,
you tell me what he's going to say next.
Is the opening of the cafe present
in all the conditions and
causes for it to open
in a way that it leans on
them or it is resting on them?
And you say, "No." And I say, "Why?"
And you say, "Because we can't observe it
at that point in time."
Then I say, "Then what
will Nagarjuna do next?"
What?
[student speaks off mic]
Yeah, are they disconnected?
Is it not resting on the
causes and conditions?
Then he says, GAL TE RGYU DANG RKYEN
RNAMS KYI TSOGS PA LA 'BRAS BU
MED NA YANG NI MI 'THAD DE
MED NA YANG means,
And if it's not leaning on
the causes and conditions,
or if it's not present there resting
on the causes and conditions,
it's also impossible.
Right? It's that Nagarjunian options.
Both options are impossible.
We need a...
Give me the Tibetan word for $100.
PHUN GSUM PA
Oh my God.
[students Chattering]
Connie, $100.
Collect it from Jigme
when she comes back, okay?
She's visiting her relatives in California
from Holland.
Okay, so...
It's also incorrect to say
that the opening of the cafe
is not resting upon the
causes and conditions
in the time of the causes and conditions
because MYU GU LTA BU'I RGYU RNAMS
DANG NI RKYEN DAG KYANG
DE'I RGYU RKYEN MA YIN PA
Then there would be no
necessary relationship
between the opening of the cafe
and the conditions for
the opening of the cafe
if the opening of the cafe
were not necessarily dependent
of those causes and conditions.
And in that case
he says, "you could use..."
Take the picture, Tim.
"You can use a lump of coal
[students giggling]
to open the cafe."
Apparently in Tibet, this is like,
if you want to give an example
of some ridiculous thing
that could be the cause
of what you're talking about,
if that wasn't the cause
as it was supposed to be,
you'd say... I'd say rabbit
turd, or something like that.
He said lump of coal.
RDO SOL, RDO SOL, which you'll never see.
RDO SOL means coal rock.
Then a coal rock should...
Then coal rocks... then
ready to operate...I'm sorry
Operating cafes...
Cafes on their opening day should pop out
of random coal rocks laying
around on the ground
if there didn't have to be
some relationship between them.
Got it?
All right we got through
that one. God bless.
Let's see if it gets easier.
You're always hoping it gets easier
and easier and it doesn't.
By the time you're hoping it
gets easier it's hopeless.
Okay.
BRGYUD NAS SKYE BA DGAG PA
If the result of the cafe opening
doesn't pop directly out of
the causes and conditions
coming together, is it a possibility
that it pops out indirectly?
I'll say it again.
If it's not the case that
the open cafe pops out
of the coming together of
the causes and conditions
for the opening of the cafe,
then can the causes and
conditions coming together
somehow in time create
the opening of the cafe?
Meaning after some time has passed.
Is there somehow an interim period
between the convening of the
necessary causes and conditions
and the popping up of the cafe,
where we could get the cinnamon rolls?
Connie's ultimate challenge:
[students laugh]
make the same taste with
all healthy ingredients
as the signature product of the cafe.
[students Laugh]
I just see JB like a chemist, mad chemist,
With his, what's that sugar called?,
Monk's Fruit sugar,
trying to get the taste
of a cinnamon roll.
The odds are not very great.
Here we go.
Here's the verse.
,GAL TE RGYU YIS 'BRAS BU LA,
,RGYU BYIN NAS NI 'GAG 'GYUR NA,
,GANG BYIN PA DANG GANG 'GAGS PA'I,
,RGYU YI BDAG NYID GNYIS SU 'GYUR,
,GAL TE RGYU YIS ‘BRAS BU LA,
,RGYU MA BYIN PAR ‘GAG ‘GYUR NA,
,RGYU ‘GAGS NAS NI SKYES PA YI,
,’BRAS BU DE DAG RGYU MED ‘GYUR,
What time we stop, Tim?
Sorry.
Yeah, in four...
30 minutes from now, five o'clock.
Okay, good.
All right, here we go.
Now, to understand or
to appreciate this verse,
can you bring the verse back?
I want you to appreciate
a certain word here,
which is BYIN.
It's the second word
here in the second line,
and it's the second
word in the third line.
BYIN
BYIN is obviously
related to the word give.
So the name of the first perfection
of the six bodhisattva perfections
is SBYIN PA,
which is giving with an
S in front of it.
But here you just got BYIN.
And this is a very
unique usage of the verb
that means to
to spit out a result.
It means to spit out a result.
And it's also the verb that you use
for distilling medicines
from herbs, from medicinal herbs.
It's called BYIN.
So somehow you boil the herbs
and then they BYIN the...
they yield this special...
They give forth this medicinal liquid.
Then you throw out
the herbs that you
distilled the liquid from.
Those thrown out herbs
are allowed to monks and nuns.
They have to search the garbage cans
for the used husks.
And they're not allowed to wear new cloth
and things like that.
They're supposed to live off of
what has the society has thrown out.
It's a pretty cool idea, actually.
So get this feeling.
When you're talking about cause and effect
what would the word BYIN mean?
Or when you're talking
about the convergence
of causes and conditions,
what would the word BYIN mean?
It spit out the open cafe.
The open cafe squirted
out, like the medicine
out of the herbs,
after they're boiled, as they're boiled.
So try to get in your mind this concept
that maybe has no
particular word in English
of causes and conditions assembling
in the final moment, and then poof,
they spit out a cafe on the opening day.
Okay?
And we're going to talk
about the status of the cause
before the spitting, during the spitting,
and after the spitting.
We're going to talk about the status
of the causes and conditions
that came together
after they have spit out the finished cafe,
or as they're spitting
out the finished cafe,
or even after.
Did I say after?
Or before.
Here we go.
GAL TE RGYUS RANG GI 'BRAS BU LA DNGOS
SU SKYED PA'I NUS PA BYIN NAS
'BRAS BU'I SNGAR 'GAGS PAS
If it's the case
that the cause,
I don't know how to say it,
if it's the case that the cause
exhibits its power to
produce something.
If it's the case that the cause
ejects the result,
spits out the result,
NUS PA BYIN NAS
and then wears itself out, okay?
Here we go.
Is it the case that once
the causes and conditions
for the cafe to open have spit out a cafe
on the opening day,
then do they exhaust themselves?
And it says, "Yes." I
mean those particular...
he money that you saved
for the opening on the first day
has spit out the cafe, and
when the cafe is there
that money is gone already.
So is it the case
that in the direct
production of the result,
the cause has worn itself out,
has exhausted itself before the result?
Or when?
- [Student] After?
- After the result?
He's asking,
'BRAS BU'I SNGAR 'GAGS PAS
Let's say that the BYIN
power, the production power,
spitting out power of
the seed it has exhausted
by the time the cafe opens.
Let's say that.
'GAGS PAS SNGAR GYI RIGS PAS MI GNOD DO
This is the other guy.
He says "Look, I don't see
why you have a problem, Nagarjuna."
When all the money, and all the workers,
and all the uncooked food has
come together, and spit out
the cafe on the first day
of the cafe's opening,
then yeah, they have used up
their power by definition.
That's what causes do.
They wear themselves out
by creating their results.
He says, "I don't see a problem."
That's his position. What's
Nagarjuna's position?
GAL TE RGYU YIS NI 'BRAS BU LA BYED RGYU
BYIN NAS NI 'GAG PAR 'GYUR NA
If the cause exhausts itself
in producing the result,
'BRAS BU LA GANG BYIN PA'I
BYED RGYU DANG GANG ZHIG 'GAGS PA'I
RGYU YI BDAG NYID GNYIS SU
RDZAS SO SO BAR 'GYUR NA
Then in that case, the
cafe that was spit out
and the cause that spit it out
can no longer have a relationship,
because the causes used
themselves up to spit it up.
A cause that has exhausted itself
and therefore gone out of existence
cannot have a relationship
with an open cafe.
All right? Got it? [Laughs]
BYIN PA'I BYED RGYU DANG GANG ZHIG
'GAGS PA' RGYU YI BDAG NYID GNYIS SU
RDZAS SO SO BAR 'GYUR NA DE MI RIGS
TE, DE GNYIS KA'ANG RGYUR MTSUNG
PAS 'BRAS BU'I SNGAR 'GAG DZOG PAR
If the result somehow had to
make contact with the cause
that had worn itself out, then the result
should have worn itself out also.
I'll say it again.
If the finished result
somehow has a relationship
with a seed, or a convening
of causes and conditions,
which has already worn
itself out, then something
that does exist is having a relationship
with something that no longer exist.
And that's not possible.
If the cause uses itself
up to produce the result,
that's illogical, because the result
could never have contact with the cause
because the cause would be gone
by the time the result occurs.
Then there would be no cause and effect.
And then our lump of
coal could open the cafe.
Because there's no
connection there either.
Everything that didn't have a connection
could cause the cafe to open.
That's what we're really hoping.
[students and instructor laugh]
All right.
DE GNYIS KA'ANG RGYUR MTSUNG PAS
Yea and he further says
that the other option
is that in the moment
that it would spit out, the result ended
because it was spit
out by an ending cause.
And only things of the same
nature can touch each other.
So if the cause exhausts
itself to produce the result,
then if they have contact,
if that particular
result could have contact
with that particular kind of cause,
then that would have to be a result
that was blinking out of existence
even as it came into existence.
because that's what its brother is doing.
and they are holding hands.
I'm not even going to
try the picture, okay?
Give it up, Tim.
Okay.
GAL TE RGYU YIS NI
'BRAS BU LA BYED RGYU MA
BYIN PAR SNGA LOGS NAS
'GAG PAR 'GYUR NA NI
MI 'THAD DE, RGYU 'GAGS
PA'I RJES NAS NI SKYES PA
YI 'BRAS BU MYU GU
LTA BU DE DAG NI RGYU LAS
DNGOS SU MI SKYE BA KHO
NAR 'GYUR BAS RGYU MED DU
'BYUNG BAR 'GYUR BA'I SKYON YOD BA'I PHYIR
GAL TE RGYU YIS NI 'BRAS BU
LA BYED RGYU MA BYIN PAR
Now if the cause could produce the result
before the cause had exhausted itself.
Okay?
If the cause could produce the result
before it had exhausted
itself in the producing.
There's a problem if
it exhausts itself totally
in the producing
because then the result doesn't
have anybody to connect with.
So maybe the other guy is going to say,
"You know what? Most of the
causes wears itself out
and then the result happens."
So then there's still a relationship.
There's still some cause
there to have relationship.
'BRAS BU MYU GU LTA BU DE
DAG NI RGYU LAS DNGOS SU
MI SKYE BA KHO NAR 'GYUR
BAS RGYU MED DU 'BYUNG BAR
'GYUR BA'I SKYON YOD BA'I PHYIR TE,
RGYU MED DU 'BYUNG BAR
Then, somehow if the cause
were to disappear before it,
before the result was all the way out?
RGYU 'GAGS PA'I RJES NAS NI SKYES PA YI
'BRAS BU MYU GU LTA BU DE DAG NI RGYU LAS
DNGOS SU MI SKYE BA KHO NAR 'GYUR BAS
In that... I'm sorry.
Let's say it in a different way.
If the cause exhausted
itself, there was a break,
and then the result came
out, that's also impossible.
If the cause exhausts
itself, takes a break,
and then the result comes
out, that's also impossible
because something like
the sprout coming out
would have to arise without
the presence of the cause.
The sprout would have to come out
after a moment has passed,
in which the seed already disappeared.
It would have to be a gap.
RGYU MED DU ‘BYUNG BAR ‘GYUR BA’I
SKYON YOD BA’I PHYIR TE,
Why? ‘BRAS BU DANG RGYU ‘GAGS PA
RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB NA
If the stopping of the result
and the stopping of the cause
existed by nature,
RGYU LA BRTEN PA YANG RANG
BZHIN GYIS YOD DGOS LA,
YOD NA 'BRAS BU DE 'BYUNG BA YANG
RGYU MED DU 'BYUNG RIGS PA'I PHYIR,
‘BRAS BU DANG RGYU ‘GAGS PA
RANG BZHIN GYIS GRUB NA
If the ending of the cause
and the ending of the result
existed from their own side,
DE RGYU LA BRTEN PA YANG
then the relying of the
result on the cause,
RANG BZHIN GYIS YOD DGOS LA
that relationship would
have to exist by nature.
YOD NA
If the relationship
between the result and the
cause existed by nature,
'BRAS BU DE 'BYUNG BA YANG RGYU MED DU
'BYUNG RIGS PA'I PHYIR,
then the result could
happen without the cause.
If the relationship existed by nature,
because then the result
would exist by nature
and existing by nature
implies that you don't
depend on some other thing.
DE LTAR NA RGYU 'GAGS ZIN NAS 'BRAS BU
SKYE DGOS NA DE MI 'THAD DE,
Therefore, it's illogical to say
that the cause has worn itself out
and then the result came,
after the cause has worn itself out. Why?
RGYU 'GAGS ZIN PA DANG 'BRAS BU SKYES
ZIN PA GNYIS DUS MNYAM PA'I PHYIR,
Because in that case
the time of the exhausting of the cause
and the time of the
wearing out of the result
should be simultaneous,
because they have a relationship:
one must be present when
the other is present.
Do the cause and effect
have a relationship? Yes.
Should one be present
when the other is present?
Yes, you can't have a relationship
if two people are not
in the room together.
Well, is the cause wearing
itself out at that moment?
Yes. So, okay, the result
is also wearing itself out.
So in the final moment of
the cause doing its thing,
the result will blink out of existence.
Why? They're holding
hands in the same room.
It can't be that the cause disappears
and then the result appears
because there would be
nobody to hold hands with.
So if it's the case that the cause
is wearing itself out
to produce the result,
then the result would have
to be wearing itself out
at the same time that the
cause is wearing itself out.
And they should both pop out
of existence at the same time.
Okay!
Something easier now.
I promise.
The whole structure of this chapter was,
I don't know if you remember
because it was a long time ago,
does the perfect convention,
convening of causes
and conditions occur
before result pops out,
or somehow simultaneous
to the result popping out,
or somehow does the
result popped out first
and then they convene?
Three possibilities, right?
We're going on to the second possibility,
which is what?
They are simultaneous.
The convening of the causes and conditions
of the opening of the cafe happen
at the same time as the
opening of the cafe.
Let's look at this puzzle.
We just established, by the way,
that they cannot come together
before the cafe opens.
[instructor coughs]
Now we look at,
is it possible for them to
happen at the same time?
Sorry. [Coughs] Sorry.
,GAL TE TSOGS DANG LHAN CIG TU,
,'BRAS BU YANG NI SKYE 'GYUR NA,.
[Coughs] I'm sorry.
If it were the case that the
result of the cafe opening
popped up at the same time
as the final payment came in for the loan,
,SKYED PAR BYED DANG BSKYED BYA GANG,
,DUS GCIG PAR NI THAL BAR 'GYUR,
then the cause spitting out the result
and the result spitted out by the cause
should be simultaneous. Okay?
If the convening of the
causes and conditions
and the opening of the
cafe somehow overlapped,
then you couldn't divide
the cause from the result.
There would be no clear distinction
between what was opening the cafe
and the cafe being opened.
GAL TE RGYU RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA NI 'BRAS BU
DANG LHAN CIG SKYES PA NYID 'BRAS BU'I
SKYED BYED DU 'GYUR RO ZHE NA,
If it's the case that
the convening of the causes
and conditions happens
at the same time as the
coming out of the result.
If you say that,
GAL TE RGYU RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA DANG LHAN CIG TU
'BRAS BU YANG NI SKYE BAR 'GYUR NA NI
MI 'THAD DE
It would be impossible,
it would be incorrect to say
that the cafe opened at the same moment
that everything you need
for the cafe to open
finally came together.
Why?
SKYED PAR BYED PA RGYU DANG BSKYED PAR BYA BA
'BRAS BU GANG YIN PA DE NI DUS GCIG TU
YOD PAR NI THAL BAR 'GYUR BA'I PHYIR,
In that case, they would
have to be simultaneous,
the opening of the cafe
and the final moment
of all the stuff needed
for the cafe to open,
would be happening at the same time,
probably the day before the cafe opened.
Right, okay?
DE LTAR MI RUNG STE, DUS MNYAM PA LA
BSKYED BYA SKYED BYED MA
MTHONG BA'I PHYIR RO,,
And that's incorrect
because we never see a case
where the thing which produces an effect
and the effect that is
produced by that thing
are never simultaneous.
There's always a time progression, right?
First the cause happens
and then the result happens.
It's not that they could be simultaneous.
Okay.
GSUM PA NI
What's the third choice?
This is the most interesting one to me.
Yeah.
The causes and conditions
for the cafe to open
happen after the cafe opened.
Which is what we were hoping.
[instructor and students laugh]
That's the one we've been
praying for, illogically.
Okay, here we go.
,GAL TE TSOGS PA'I SNGA ROL TU,
,'BRAS BU SKYES PAR 'GYUR NA NI,
,RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS MED PA NI,
,'BRAS BU RGYU MED 'BYUNG BAR 'GYUR,
,GAL TE TSOGS PA'I SNGA ROL TU,
If before the causes and conditions
that finally came together
,'BRAS BU SKYES PAR 'GYUR NA NI,
If the cafe opened
before the causes and
conditions were ready,
,RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS MED PA NI,
,'BRAS BU RGYU MED 'BYUNG BAR 'GYUR,
then a result would have happened
without a cause.
If the cafe could open
before we got all the money,
and the food, and all that,
then you'd have a result
that didn't have a cause,
which is what we are hoping for.
Now,
he goes to the Abhidharma school.
And I thought it would be fun
for you guys to go there.
He goes to the Abhidharma school.
I thought it would be
fun for us to go there.
So, here we go.
BYE BRAG SMRA BA NA RE,
'BRAS BU RNAMS RGYU RKYEN
TSOGS PA'I SNGA
ROL GYI MA 'ONGS PA'I
DUS SU GNAS PA YANG
YIN LA RGYU RKYEN TSOGS PAS NI
DA LTA BA'I GNAS SKABS SKYED KYI,
RDZAS NI SNGA PHYIR YANG GNAS SO ZHE NA,
They have a special idea,
and I believe is a reflection
of the Sankya idea, okay?
'BRAS BU RNAMS RGYU RKYEN
TSOGS PA'I SNGA ROL GYI
The result of causes and
conditions coming together could...
I got to think about this.
Saying that the causes and conditions
for the opening of the
cafe have come together
is posited on the opening of the cafe.
Therefore, the opening of the cafe
did happen before the
causes and conditions
of the opening of the cafe happened.
It exists as a future certainty,
or something like that,
which is a big discussion in Buddhism.
If all the necessary causes
and conditions are present,
could you even prevent
the opening of the cafe?
Is it possible to prevent
And we'd say "No." Okay?
- Which causes and
conditions you're saying?
- Oh, the causes and conditions
for the opening of the cafe.
- Oh, are they causes and conditions
of the opening of the cafe?
- Yes.
- So the cafe must be open
while the causes and conditions are there,
because they are causes and conditions
for the opening of the cafe.
The opening of the cafe owns
those causes and conditions.
Therefore, the causes and conditions
have to happen after
the opening of the cafe,
because you can't call
them causes and conditions
for the opening of the cafe,
unless there is an opening of the cafe.
And this is true. And this
goes back to an ancient point
made in the first ACI course,
with the spear analogy.
When soldiers
get home from fighting all day in battle,
they would sit down for their meal
after they put their spears,
stack them together
in a tripod. This is
the ancient example.
They come home from a
hard day of fighting,
they're going to sit
down and have some pizza,
and they stack their spears.
They have their spears point up,
resting on each other
like a tripod, and that's
because if the enemy
suddenly shows up for pizza,
they can grab their spear quickly
and start poking people.
And the analogy in Pabongka
Rinpoche's commentary
to "The Three Principal Paths",
which I'm sure you remember
from ACI Course One, is that
it is true that results depend on causes
but causes equally depend on results,
because they cannot be called causes
until the result has come out.
You can't call the investment money
of the opening the cafe
the investment money for
the opening of the cafe,
it cannot be called the cause
for the opening of the cafe
until the cafe opens.
Then you can say it's a cause
because otherwise there's
no opening of the cafe
that had the cause.
Got it?
It can't be a cause for
the opening of the cafe
until there is an opening of the cafe.
Only when the cafe opens
and there's a result
can you say it had a cause.
Before the cafe opens, it's just a thing
that's going on.
It doesn't have a second half.
Once the second half is
complete, the result,
then the money, the
food, Rosa's effort, they
can be called causes,
but only after the result comes out.
So they're kind of going there. Who?
The Abhidharmists.
RGYU RKYEN TSOGS PAS NI
DA LTA BA'I GNAS SKABS SKYED KYI,
RDZAS NI
SNGA PHYIR YANG GNAS SO
So in that sense, the opening of the cafe
did exist during the convening
of its causes and conditions.
Otherwise you couldn't have called them
conditions for the opening.
There must have been some kind
of opening of cafe around
for these things to be called
the causes and conditions
for the opening of the cafe.
Then we say
DE NI MI RIGS TE
"Hey, that's dumb."
John Brady is the only
one who was doubting it.
Now, you're correct.
That's not right.
GAL TE RGYU RKYEN GYI TSOGS PA'I
SNGA ROL DU
00:39:57,756 --> 00:39:57,589
'BRAS BU SKYES PA
STE GRUB PAR GYUR NA NI,
If the result of the cafe opening
were somehow to be present
before the causes and conditions
were finally brought together,
'BRAS BU DE RGYU DANG RKYEN RNAMS LA
BLTOS PA MED PAR 'GYUR
That result would no longer rely
upon those causes and
conditions for its existence.
If the cafe opening existed
during the time of the
causes and conditions,
then we would have to say,
that the opening of the cafe
was not contingent upon
those causes and conditions
because it was even there
before they could begin.
If they are simultaneous,
there's no dependence.
Okay?
DE LTA NA DE YI 'BRAS BU
RGYU MED PAR 'BYUNG BA
CAN DU 'GYUR BA'I SKYON YOD PA'I PHYIR
And in that case, you could
have an opening of the cafe
before you had the causes and conditions.
And then where's the causation there?
Hang in there. Okay?
Don't you say, "Oh,
this is stupid, I'll go
on to Lam Rim or something."
Don't think like that.
Struggle with it. What's
the worst that can happen?
We covered it today.
You get born into a world
were there's no Buddhism
but you're the only one
who figures everything out.
That's the worst that can happen.
All right.
GNYIS PA LA GNYIS, RGYU
'BRAS NGO BO GCIG PA'I
PHYOGS DGAG PA DANG, NGO BO
THA DAD PA'I PHYOGS DGAG PA
Is a cause and its result one thing?
Or is a cause and its
result separate things?
This is an old...
You're all like
"Oh, that's Utpala's book."
We already know the answer to that
but I don't remember."
[students laugh]
Okay.
Is it true that to be the
cause is to be the result?
Or is it the case that
to be the cause is to be
different from the result?
That's the question.
And we're going to cover
the first possibility.
Is it true that to be the
cause is to be the result?
Here's the verse.
,GAL TE RGYU 'GAGS 'BRAS BU NA,
,RGYU NI KUN DU 'PHO BAR 'GYUR,
,SNGON SKYES PA YI RGYU YANG NI,
,YANG SKYE BAR NI THAL BAR 'GYUR,
GAL TE RGYU ‘GAGS NAS
‘BRAS BU’I BDAG NYID DU
GNAS PA YIN NO
This is an interesting concept.
And it's called 'PHO BA.
And here's another meaning
of the word 'PHO BA,
but it's similar. You can tell.
Someone comes up and says,
how do you say it?
"The cause transforms into the result."
Okay, you don't have
to talk about the cause
starting, stopping and then the result
either starting, or stopping,
or somehow they overlap.
You don't have to talk like that.
The cause transforms into the result.
Which is a reasonable
way to say it. Right?
So in Nagarjuna's literature,
it is called 'PHO BA.
'PHO BA usually refers to what? For us.
- [Student 1] Change of life?
- Yeah, you change lifetimes.
You change rebirth. Right?
You move from one
rebirth to another.
And here he's talking about
the identity of the cause
shifting into an identity as a result,
but it's the same thing.
It's one person who used to
be Bob and changed to John.
But it's the same person.
The result is the cause in
different clothes. [giggles]
The cause changed its pants
and that's called result.
But it's still the cause.
He just changed his pants.
[laughs] Okay, all right.
That's an interesting idea.
Let's see what Nagarjuna says.
Are we okay on time?
Time, Tim? Time, Tim, Tim, time?
Five more minutes. Let's
see how much we can do.
DE NI MI 'THAD DE
I don't like that.
GAL TE RGYU 'GAGS NAS 'BRAS
BU'I BDAG NYID DU 'PHO NA
So are you saying that the cause stops
and then transforms into the result?
Is that what you're saying?
The cause comes to an end
and then it slips into
result and kind of changes?
Is that what you're saying
when you say 'PHO BA?
Is that what you mean when
you say "moves"? Okay?
Transfers?
Transitions into result?
Is that what you're saying?
And the guy says, "Yeah."
And then he says, "Well it sounds...
ZLOS GAR MKHAN CHA LUGS GZHAN
DANG GZHAN DU BSGYUR
Can you put that up on the screen?
It's kind of cute.
Second, yeah.
ZLOS GAR MKHAN CHA LUGS
GZHAN DANG GZHAN DU BSGYUR
Is a beautiful example.
ZLOS GAR means the ancient
Sanskrit and Tibet dramas
which were acted out on a small stage,
like the Greek comedies,
and the Greek dramas.
ZLOS GAR means
a stage play,
like the classical Greek
tragedies and things like that.
It's called ZLOS GAR.
ZLOS GAR MKHAN means an actor
in one of those plays.
So let's take an actor
CHA LUGS GZHAN DANG GZHAN DU BSGYUR
So you're saying when a
cause produces a result
it's like the actor was playing
one character in the first act
and then he ran backstage
and changed clothes
and came out in the second act,
and played a different character.
Is a beautiful example,
because it kind of is the...
That's the picture we have when
he described 'PHO BA, right?
The cause put on different
pants and became the result.
It's the same idea.
The same thing, essentially,
put on a different outfit
and came out as a different actor,
but it's the same guy.
The cause and the result are the same guy
in different costumes during
different acts of the play.
Is that what you're saying?
RGYU NI DUS KUN DU 'PHO
BA TZAM DU 'GYUR GYI,
So you're saying causes
just kind of change
their outer appearance
and become results, right?
'BRAS BU SNGAR MED GSAR DU
MI SKYE BAR 'GYUR BA'I PHYIR TE,
So are you saying a new
result has come out or not?
DE LTA NA RGYU DE RTAG PAR 'GYUR BAS
That's an interesting idea. If the result
is the power of the cause
dressed up in different clothes,
then the cause hasn't really
changed in its essence.
It's just put on new clothes.
And in that case, what was
there at 3:00
is still there at 3:01.
And in that case, it's
RTAG PA
What does that mean? It's unchanging.
It's an unchanging functioning thing,
which is a four letter word.
- [Student 2] I though of the word fixed.
- Fixed?
- [Student 2] It's fixed.
- Yeah, you can say fixed.
But you know, in classical Buddhism,
it's almost like saying a dirty word.
When you say "This thing does something,
but by doing something
it doesn't change."
That's totally illegal
in all of Buddhism.
So if you're going to say,
"The cause is the result
in different clothes,"
then what you're talking
about is cause and effect
where nothing changes.
It's just impossible.
It's totally against all Buddhism.
We're going to stop there
because everyone has a headache.
[students laugh]
Oh, one more line.
The other option is that the
cause that changes its clothes
and becomes the result, would
just keep changing its clothes,
and then it would be an
infinite regression.
So that's called
THUG MED
THUG MED PA is an idea in Buddhism
that the same thing would just...
there's no reason why it
shouldn't just keep happening
over and over again, endlessly.
So I don't know, a peach tree
seed creates a peach tree,
and then it creates another peach tree,
and it creates another
peach tree, and so on.
Because it's all the same seed
in different clothing.
Okay. Where are we now?
Next up, in the next class,
it's a very interesting
extended discussion
of seven different possibilities
of how a cause gets ready
to trigger a result.
So we're going to get
seven different ideas
about how a cause warms
up to produce a result.
And there's a very interesting discussion
of all the possible variations
on how does a cause warm
up to produce a result.
And what does that look like?
We're going to discuss seven
different possibilities.
They're all impossible.
All seven possibilities are impossible.
And we'll go to that next.
Just to set you up, let
me make a mark here.
I want to give you some hope.
That's going to lead us
on to chapter 21.
So we'll be running to discuss
another topic after that.
So hang in there.
We'll talk about seven different ways
in which a cause warms
up to produce a result.
And then we'll get free from this chapter
and we'll go to another
chapter very quickly.
[student laughs]
All right? Okay.
See you in the next class.